The Perseverance rover is on its way to Mars.
In February, it will land in a fabulous area
called Jezero crater.
It's right there on that edge between the
land and the ancient ocean.
What do we expect to find?
There could've been a habitable environment
in that watershed area that picked up some
potential biosignatures and deposited into
the delta and got preserved.
Hi, I’m Jim Green, Chief Scientist at NASA
and this is Gravity Assist.
On this Season of Gravity Assist we’re looking
for life beyond Earth.
I'm here with Dr. Kennda Lynch, and she is
an astrobiologist and a geomicrobiologist
studying life in extremes.
She works at the Lunar and Planetary Institute
in Houston, Texas.
Welcome, Kennda, to Gravity Assist.
Thank you.
It's so great to be here.
Well, you know, your current research really
focuses on the studying of paleo-lake basins
here on Earth, and so that makes you a perfect
expert to be involved in the Perseverance
rover since it's going to Jezero crater and
land on an ancient lake basin, doesn't it?
Umm, I, I would say it makes me one of several
really good experts that are really excited
at the fact that we're going to Jezero.
Well, let's first discuss what we know about
the Earth's paleo-lake basins.
Absolutely.
What we know about Earth lake basins is a
lot of our paleo-lake basins, these were ancient
lakes that were, in a lot of cases, very,
very big, very deep lakes.
For example, Lake Bonneville, where my field
site is, was an ancient lake of the Pleistocene
era, and at one point, it was
a thousand foot in depth.
It was very big, very deep, actually freshwater
lake.
But, over time, because it was a closed basin
lake and we had climate change, the lake started
to dry out.
It didn't have any outflow, so everything
just evaporated,
There's many of these across the world that
we study.
There's the Great Salt Lake here in Utah. We also have
Death Valley also has paleo-lakes in it.
The Salar de Uyuni in Bolivia also has one.
We have paleo-lakes in China in the Qaidam
Basin.
So all these big lakes dried into these amazing
playa environments where we have all of these
lake sediments, we sometimes have occasional
very, very shallow lakes that can develop
in these environments, but we have amazing
microbial diversity that can be found in these
lake basin sediments after the lake went away,
and that's what I like to study.
Well, what exactly are you looking for when
you get these sediments?
We're looking at a couple of different things.
Initially, we wanted to just try to understand
what these ecosystems look like.
There really hasn't been a lot of research,
believe it or not, in these kind of systems
because people didn't really understand that
they could be very, very rich in life.
So the first thing we do is we do a lot of
a lot of heavy biology, so a lot of looking for DNA
and trying to understand what we call the
phylogeny.
Who's there, how diverse they are, what does
the ecosystem, what do the microbial communities
look like? So that's, you know
A lot of the first work that I did was understanding
who's there and what they look like.
Then the next thing we look for is how are
they interacting with the environment, how
are they interacting with the geochemistry,
how are they living there, what are they eating,
what are they breathing, how are they getting
their energy, how are they interacting, all
of these kinds of things.
So we look for that, and we try to understand
that.
Kennda, can you tell me about a particularly
memorable experience you had out in the field?
Oh, wow, there's so many. I might,
I'm going to give you two quick little ones.
Umm, we
When we were at the center of the basin we
where there's an actual a
an actual well that my colleagues
had put in permanently, we found a little
mouse hanging out in the well, just hanging
out in the shade of the well, and he had somehow
gotten onto the playa.
But he was hanging out there during the heat
of the day.
Well, the next day, we came back to one of
my boreholes that was about a mile away.
That mouse was in my borehole using the borehole
as shade.
So he had, overnight, had gone that whole
mile, mile and a half, and was using our borehole
as a refuge for the day heat.
It was very cute, and we got pictures of it.
Then the second memorable experience was when
we got our UTV stuck in some of the playa
mud.
That was a challenge.
You know, the first mission to find perchlorates
on Mars was Phoenix, but even Curiosity has
confirmed that there are perchlorates but
not everywhere.
What are perchlorates, and tell us a little
bit about how are they important?
So perchlorates are what we call chlorine
oxyanions.
It's a chlorine atom surrounded by four oxygen
atoms, and it's a really, really, really big
oxidizer very similar to oxygen, so it gives
the same
kind of energy release that oxygen does.
In fact, here on Earth, we use perchlorates
as part of solid rocket fuel because when
you light it up, it really gives a lot of
energy that helps our rockets take off.
People experience perchlorates every day in
things like firecrackers.
But we also know that perchlorate occurs naturally
on Earth and, of course, on Mars.
And on Mars, we see more perchlorate on Mars than
we see anywhere on Earth, and so it's this
incredible potential energy resource that
life could use to generate energy and sustain
an ecosystem.
The other reason, which is not as exciting,
but perchlorates on Earth, they can be toxic
to humans, so we want to understand perchlorates
so that we can make sure that it doesn't affect
our astronauts when we send them to Mars,
so that we can mitigate the perchlorates and
make sure that they don't make our astronauts
sick when we send our first human mission
to Mars.
Ok. We are at our first sampling point.
This field site that you went to, the Pilot
field site, where is it at, and why did you
choose that?
So Pilot Valley Basin is a part of the Great
Salt Lake Desert, which basically encompasses
pretty much most of northwestern Utah.
So basically, once you get past Salt Lake City,
the rest of it is the Great Salt Lake Desert,
and Pilot Valley is a sub-basin of that desert
that actually because of how it's nestled
in between two mountain ranges is kinda off on its
own, it's all Jeep roads to get there, it's
not that easy to get to.
So there hasn't been a lot of anthropogenic
input onto Pilot Valley, whereas other basins
in the Great Salt Lake Desert, they do a lot
of salt-mining, a lot of economic geology.
Pilot Valley has been off on its own and pretty
much left pristine.
And how I found this environment actually very
much relates to the Phoenix mission and our
discovery of perchlorate.
I was working with Dr. Sam Kounaves, who was
a Co-I on Phoenix at the time and is one of my
my long-term mentors and definitely a wonderful,
wonderful scientist.
And I was working with him on his sensors, his
wet chemistry sensors, and during the Phoenix
mission, I was in grad school and he called
me.
He called me and I think he actually might've
called me from JPL and said, "Kennda, do you
know anything about perchlorate," and started
me down this road about looking at perchlorate
and microbes that can use perchlorate.
The following summer, I was driving to Ames
Research Center to start my Harriet Jenkins
Predoctoral Fellowship summer portion.
I was driving through Utah and looking at
the Great Salt Lake Desert, and I had done
all this research about perchlorate and where
it lives in the Atacama, and I'm looking at
the Great Salt Lake Desert and I'm like, "I
wonder if there's perchlorate here.
That would be kind of a neat environment to
study."
So I wrote a little mini-proposal to get the
summer internship money the next summer from
my school, and I went out and did a field
expedition, and literally it changed my whole
direction of my dissertation.
And you, it just kind of keeps
keeps getting more and more interesting
and more and more fun every time we go out there.
Well you know, there are other places in the
solar system, you know, that we were
thinking of looking for life, like Europa.
Are you doing any research on Earth that relates
to Europa?
Definitely some of the work that we're doing
in my basin.
We're looking at perchlorates reducing bacteria in the hypersaline systems of my basin
One of my recent research papers that just
came out last summer, where we basically documented
our first discovery of perchlorate reducing
microbes cohabitating in an area there was
actually also naturally-occurring perchlorate,
something that's never been documented before.
So, now, we have a relevant Earth analog ecosystem
to learn about how perchlorate reducing microbes
can live in what on Earth is an extreme environment
but would be more of a normal environment
on Mars or Europa, living in a brine or a
salty environment in Mars and Europa.
I remember that once you did a talk called
"All Life Poops."
Does that mean that even bacteria has waste,
and could we find traces of that in any of
the samples that we bring back, whether it's
from Mars
or flying through the plume over Europa?
Yep, indeed.
All life takes in energy and creates waste
products or, for lack of a better word, poops,
and it is indeed often these waste products
that turn into biosignatures
or possible biosignatures of life.
For example, we're breathing poop right now.
We are breathing tree poop.
So oxygen is tree poop.
So oxygen, molecular oxygen, is a potential
biosignature
that we look for in extrasolar planets.
So, absolutely, poop can be a biosignature.
Wow.
You're absolutely right.
I just never thought of it that way.
I know.
It's so funny.
When I show kids, some of them go ... and
try to hold their breath.
They're like, "I don't want to breathe poop,"
and I'm like, "Don't have a choice."
You need that, okay?
You need that poop.
That's what makes different types of life
coexist together, and in fact, we need that
oxygen production from our plants.
Yep, absolutely.
Just as they need the CO2 production that
we create.
Yep.
So that's what creates a biosphere is that
important relationship between the different
species of life.
Exactly.
So, Kennda, what about Perseverance is getting
you really excited?
When that lands in Jezero crater, what do
you want it to do?
I am so excited about what we call the bottomset
deposits.
These are these really, really fine deposits,
really fine grains.
They're usually mostly made up of clays and
carbonates on Earth.
They're really small particles that deposit
in the lake basin and at the front of the
delta that can make these great sediments
where we can preserve organics and biosignatures.
I am so excited for Perseverance to go and
start taking a look at those particular deposits
in the crater.
We're going to have some of the best chances
of finding preserved organics in those deposits
because that's an environment on Earth where
those kind of lake bed deposits or delta deposits,
we know we get a lot of concentrated carbon
that gets preserved and stabilized very well
in those kind of deposits.
So I'm really excited about the bottomsets.
It's right there on that edge between the
land and the ancient ocean, and this river
was dumping into that when this impact occurred
and created this huge crater we now call Jezero.
Would you think we might be able to find some
biomolecules if you've got complex carbon,
a material that we're also finding?
Is there a hope that we could do that?
You know, I really do think so because what's
really amazing about these bottomset deposits
is that because of the lake environment and
the fact that we have this delta, it could
come from three potentially different habitable
environments within the Jezero crater area.
It could've come from up in the watershed,
and the watershed is that area where all the
water kinda flowed together into one big river or stream
and deposited the water and the sediments
that created the delta.
There could've been a habitable environment
in that watershed area that picked up some
potential biosignatures and deposited into
the delta and got preserved.
It could've come from the lake itself.
Or it could've been preserved from a transitional
habitable zone like I study, this subsurface
environment where there's groundwater moving
through these sediments after the lake's gone,
and there could've been a subsurface ecosystem
that could've lived there for a time before
water retreated even deeper into Mars, and
there could've been life that could've left
some potential biosignatures there.
So we have three different potential habitable
environments that could've left biosignatures
in these deposits, so I just
I'm so excited to see what we can find out when we get samples from there.
You bring up something I hadn't really thought
about, but, indeed, with that lake over time
being eroded away and then the atmosphere
becomes very thin,
that's going to draw groundwater out.
Yeah, especially since we know now that groundwater
was a significant part of the hydrology on
Mars, that that's going to be a really important
environment for us to start to try to understand. So
Again, I'm so excited to see what we're going
to be able to find out.
Well, you've also been involved in education
and diversity efforts in what we call science,
technology, engineering, and mathematics or STEM
you know, as an acronym.
Can you tell us a little bit about what your
efforts are and what you've been doing in
this area?
I am a lifetime member of the Girl Scouts. I started
I was my mom's first Girl Scout, and my mom was a professional
worked on the professional staff, so I grew
up in girl scouting and giving back and reaching
out and educating. And so
Yeah, I've just been doing it my whole life,
all through college and undergrad.
I have mentored so many students while working
as a full-time engineer.
I've done a lot of school presentations.
And, right now
and in Grad School, you know I've mentored students and taught classes
Right now, I've got three students I'm mentoring,
two directly at the LPI, one indirectly with
a colleague who's asked me to mentor one of
their students of color, and I'm very excited
to be able to do that.
I also do a lot of STEM outreach with our
education and public engagement department
here at the Lunar and Planetary Institute.
I'm a Ford Fellow, so I interact with that
community quite a lot and try to help with
efforts to increase diversity, equity, and
inclusion across the space sciences and just
STEM in general
Well, I personally want to thank you for all
that activity.
I enjoy talking to the public and talking
about the fabulous science that we do.
You just can't stop me, and I'm just delighted
that you're doing the same.
Well, Kennda, I always like to ask my guests
to tell me what was that person, place, or
thing that happened that got them so excited,
that enabled them to become the scientist
they are today, and I call that a gravity
assist.
So, Kennda, what was your gravity assist?
Well, there was so many people along the way,
I can't recount them all, but what I will
tell you is that my biggest gravity assist,
the one that just makes me well up right now
is that my first summer internship at Kennedy
Space Center, I was a space life science training
program participant.
I won't give you a year, but it was way back
when, when the shuttle was flying.
And it was my first, you know, entry into the space world
that I'd always wanted to be a part of, and
I got accepted into that program.
And the biggest gravity assist for me was seeing
my first shuttle launch.
They let us go out and watch the shuttle launch
at Kennedy, and I got to see one of the shuttle
launches, and that first shuttle launch and
watching that spacecraft go into the air and
hearing the noise and watching the alligators
jump out of the water because it was so noisy
for them was just so inspiring and just ... I
couldn't believe that at 20 years old I was
there and I could be here and that I was a
part of the space industry finally.
So that was definitely one of my biggest gravity
assists that kept me going.
Well, that was wonderful.
Well, thanks so much for joining me today.
I've really enjoyed our discussion.
Me, too.
Thank you so much for having me.
Well, join me next time as we continue our
journey to look for life beyond Earth.
I'm Jim Green, and this is your Gravity Assist.
Find more episodes at: nasa.gov/gravityassist